Finding Aid for Ivory Photo, Ann Arbor, Michigan ca. 1927-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ivory Photo photograph collection circa 1927-1971
Ivory Photo (Firm)
31 linear feet
Ann Arbor, Michigan, photography firm. Photonegatives, and some photoprints, of images largely relating to Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan, but including Ypsilanti and other Michigan cities: buildings, businesses, houses, street scenes, community activities, and organizations; also photos of automobiles, storm damage, etc. taken to support insurance claims.
92324 UBB.2 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Robert Shipman (donor no. 6857 ), 1982.
The collection is open for research.
Melvin Allison Ivory came to Ann Arbor in the mid-1920s from Lansing, where he had done amateur photo finishing for his father's two drugstores. He from Ann Arbor High School and worked part-time doing photo finishing for his uncle, Percy Mack, who was part owner of Calkins-Fletcher Drug Company and was in charge of the camera department.
While an undergraduate at the University of Michigan, Ivory became a photographer for the Alumni Association. He continued to handle photo finishing "both amateur and professional" for Calkins-Fletcher after graduating from the university in 1931. In addition, Ivory Photographic Services became the official photographer for the Michigan Alumnus, Michiganensian, and the Bureau of Alumni Relations. Ivory married Janet Boylan in 1931.
In 1937 Mel Ivory and his brother Gail Ivory founded the Ivory Photo Engraving Company at 1030 East University Avenue in Ann Arbor. The company continued until 1944, although Gail Ivory had departed earlier to join the Navy. In 1944 Mel Ivory bought the business of photographer Oscar Mahlke, including his photo finishing equipment and contracts with local businesses. Eventually, Ivory was doing daily photo finishing for more than forty stores in Ann Arbor and neighboring towns. This work is reflected in an extensive group of photographs of stores, restaurants, factories, and other workplaces and products. Ivory also took photographs for insurance companies from the 1930s to the 1960s.
Ivory Photo moved to 606 South Main Street in 1948, where it remains to this day. When Mel Ivory died in 1972, his daughter Susan Ivory Shipman and her husband Robert Shipman took over the business. In 1982 the Shipmans sold Ivory Photo to Diane and Michael Hough.
For further information see:
Bentley Historical Library Annual Report 1982-1983, pp. 27-30
Michigan Alumnus 38 (March 19, 1932), p. 427
and
Ann Arbor News, June 25, 1982, Sec. C, p. 5.
Bentley Historical Library, Annual Report 1982-1983, pp. 27-30; Michigan Alumnus 38 (March 19, 1932), p. 427; and Ann Arbor News, June 25, 1982, Sec. C, p. 5.
The negatives are arranged according to size; prints of all sizes are filed together in one series of 9"x12" envelopes. The collection is arranged in four series: Negatives - 4"x5"; Negatives - 5"x7"; Negatives - 8"x10"; and Prints. The Negatives - 4"x5" series contains all negatives that are 4"x5" or smaller. Two Super 8 films are filed at the end of Box 25. A useful box-by-box summary outline of the contents list follows this section.
Within each series, the negatives and prints are arranged in subseries according to the town or county they represent and then according to subject matter. Subseries and further subdivisions are arranged alphabetically; photographs within a particular category are arranged chronologically. Because of their quantity, University of Michigan negatives and prints constitute a separate subseries rather than part of the Ann Arbor subseries.
The largest subseries are Ann Arbor, the University of Michigan, Ypsilanti, and Washtenaw County. The remaining subseries consist of other towns and counties in Michigan; most of these contain only a few negatives or prints. Researchers should see the contents list for the names of towns and counties represented.
Negatives - 4"x5" [boxes 1-25]
Ann Arbor [boxes 1-14]
Airports and Airplanes [box 1]
Buildings and Views [boxes 1-7]
Cemeteries [1]
Churches [1]
Gas Stations [1]
Hospitals [2]
Houses and Businesses [boxes 2-5]
Parks [5]
Public Buildings [5]
Railroad Stations and Trains [5]
Schools [5-6]
Streets [6-7]
Businesses [7-9]
Insurance Claims [boxes 9-10]
Fires [9]
Storm Damage [9]
Traffic Accidents [9-10]
Motor Vehicles [10]
Organizations and Groups [10-11]
People [11-13]
Pets and Other Animals [13]
Politics [13]
Social Life and Customs [boxes 13-14]
Community Events [13]
Dance Bands and Orchestras [13]
Funerals [13]
Parties [14]
Radio and Television Broadcasts [14]
Sports [14]
Weddings [14]
World War II [14]
University of Michigan [boxes 15-23]
Alumni Activities [15]
Athletics [15-17]
Buildings and Views [17-19]
Colleges, Schools, and Other Divisions [19-21]
Individuals and Groups [21]
Organizations [21]
Special Celebrations and Events [22]
Student Life [22-23]
World War II [23]
Bridgewater [23]
Chelsea [23]
Dexter [23]
Manchester [23]
Milan [23]
Pittsfield Township [23]
Salem Township [23]
Saline [23]
Scio Township [23]
Whitmore Lake [23]
Willow Run [23]
Ypsilanti [boxes 23-24]
Businesses [23-24]
Centennial [24]
Houses and Apartments [24]
People [24]
Rural Scenes [24]
Schools [24]
Streets and Buildings [24]
Washtenaw County [box 24]
Aerial Views [24]
Businesses [24]
Cassidy Lake Tech [24]
County Offices [24]
Farms [24]
Lakes [24]
Rural Scenes [24]
Michigan Towns and Counties (non-Washtenaw) [boxes 24-25]
Miscellaneous [25]
Buildings [25]
Businesses [25]
Churches [25]
Events [25]
People [25]
Negatives - 5"x7" [boxes 26-27]
Ann Arbor [box 26]
Airports and Airplanes [26]
Buildings and Views [26]
Churches [26]
Hospitals [26]
Houses and Businesses [26]
Railroad Stations and Trains [26]
Schools [26]
Miscellaneous [26]
Businesses [26]
Motor Vehicles [26]
Organizations and Groups [26]
People [26]
Social Life and Customs [26]
University of Michigan [boxes 26-27]
Alumni Activities [26]
Athletics [26]
Buildings and Views [26-27]
Colleges, Schools, and Other Divisions [27]
Individuals and Groups [27]
Organizations [27]
Special Celebrations and Events [27]
Student Life [27]
Ypsilanti [27]
Washtenaw County [27]
Michigan Towns and Counties (non-Washtenaw) [27]
Negatives - 8"x10" [boxes 28-30]
Ann Arbor [boxes 28-29]
Airports and Airplanes [28]
Buildings and Views [28]
Churches [28]
Gas Stations [28]
Hospitals [28]
Houses and Businesses [28]
Railroad Tracks and Crossings [28]
Schools [28]
Streets [28]
Businesses [28-29]
Insurance Claims [29]
Traffic Accidents [29]
Motor Vehicles [29]
Organizations and Groups [29]
People [29]
Social Life and Customs [29]
World War II [29]
University of Michigan [boxes 29-30]
Alumni Activities [29]
Athletics [30]
Buildings and Views [30]
Colleges, Schools, and Other Divisions [30]
Individuals and Groups [30]
Organizations [30]
Special Celebrations and Events [30]
Student Life [30]
World War II [30]
Bridgewater [30]
Dexter [30]
Manchester [30]
Milan [30]
Saline [30]
Scio? [30]
Whitmore Lake [30]
Ypsilanti [30]
Washtenaw County? [30]
Michigan Towns and Counties (non-Washtenaw) [30]
Miscellaneous [30]
Prints [box 31]
Ann Arbor [31]
Airports and Airplanes [31]
Buildings and Views [31]
Houses and Businesses [31]
Parks [31]
Railroads [31]
Schools [31]
Businesses [31]
Insurance Claims [31]
Motor Vehicles [31]
Organizations and Groups [31]
People [31]
Pets and Other Animals [31]
Social Life and Customs [31]
World War II [31]
University of Michigan [31]
Alumni Activities [31]
Athletics [31]
Buildings and Views [31]
Colleges, Schools, and Other Divisions [31]
Individuals and Groups [31]
Organizations [31]
Special Celebrations and Events [31]
Student Life [31]
World War II [31]
Dexter [31]
Milan [31]
Whitmore Lake [31]
Ypsilanti [31]
Washtenaw County [31]
Michigan Towns and Counties (non-Washtenaw) [31]
Miscellaneous [31]
Super 8 Films [25]
The Ivory Photo collection consists of an impressive array of negatives and prints taken by Ann Arbor photographer Mel Ivory from the 1920s to the early 1970s. Most of the photographs were taken by Ivory for customers, whether the University of Michigan, local businesses, or private citizens. The collection is probably most valuable for its extensive documentation of Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan, the two areas in which it bulks largest. However, because it spans a relatively long time period, the collection is also useful for illustrating changes in photography as an art and as a business, and for documenting social trends in twentieth-century America. Finally, the collection documents the career of a commercial photographer.
As a photographer for the University of Michigan in the 1920s and 1930s, Ivory took the standard pictures of campus events, buildings, and people, but the value of many photographs from this period is as much aesthetic as informational. Producing cover art for the Michigan Alumnus allowed him to experiment with unusual angles, lighting, and subject matter. (See, for example, photographs of the Clements Library and of students strolling through the Diag in the 1930s.) In stark contrast to these images is a large group of photographs of car wrecks that Ivory took for insurance companies between 1937 and 1969.
Besides providing thorough documentation of the physical plant of the University of Michigan, the Ivory collection evokes the flavor of life on campus in the 1930s and 1940s through photographs of football games and crowds, dance bands, social events, professors at work in laboratories, the Michigan Daily staff at work, and students in classrooms, libraries, and dormitories.
The Ann Arbor subseries includes numerous photographs of houses and businesses, filed by address to facilitate research into a particular building or site, as well as a rich assortment of photographs depicting life in Ann Arbor through more than four decades. There are numerous photographs of men and women at work in factories, stores, and other settings. Some show women at work in unusual settings (as cab drivers for Ace Cab Company, for example) while others depict women in stereotypically female occupations (as secretaries, store clerks, and ditto machine operators). Photographs of drug and department store display windows and of products in grocery stores illustrate trends in merchandising.
The Ivory collection is also remarkable for its documentation of social mores. Wedding photographs taken from the 1930s to the 1960s depict a variety of settings, fashions, wedding rituals, and even fads, such as a 1940 wedding at a roller rink. There is also a small group of photographs of funerals and an extensive series of portraits of children, families, and individuals.
Photographs of a depression-era hobo cooking near a railroad car, of lawn parties and country clubs, of the soap box derby and sports teams reflect diverse aspects of life in Ann Arbor. The home front during World War II is documented in views of an aluminum drive, a blitzkrieg game in a local tavern, a commuter bus with a female conductor, and the Judge Advocate General's school exercises in the Law Quad.
Although the Ypsilanti subseries is considerably smaller than the Ann Arbor and University of Michigan subseries, it contains a number of valuable photographs, such as the Cleary College photographs showing rows of students at typewriters, students relaxing on boarding house steps and in Cleary lounges and recreation rooms, and annual graduation processions. The Washtenaw County subseries contains rural scenes such as farms, country roads, and a county fair. The remaining subseries consist of businesses, street scenes, railroad stations, and a variety of other photographs representing Michigan towns and counties.
A few copy negatives made by Ivory from existing photographs are scattered throughout the collection. A late nineteenth or early twentieth-century anatomy lesson in the Medical School, for example, is filed in the "Colleges, Schools, and other Divisions" section of University of Michigan 5"x7" negatives.
The contents of the various subseries and sub-subseries are for the most part self-evident, but a few words of explanation about the Ann Arbor subseries are in order. "Buildings and Views" consists largely of exterior views of buildings. However, there are many interior scenes of people and activities in the "Churches," "Hospitals," and "Schools" sections. For example, photographs of Ann Arbor churches include views of the pastor and congregation, choirs, recreation rooms, meetings, and athletic teams in addition to interior and exterior views of the buildings. "Schools" contains photographs of sports teams, classroom scenes, social events, and buildings representing Ann Arbor public and parochial schools, but also Ann Arbor Secretarial School and Concordia College.
Researchers seeking images of commercial enterprises will find material in the "Buildings and Views" sub-subseries (listed under the street address in the "Houses and Businesses" section) and in the "Businesses" sub-subseries (under the name of the enterprise).
The "Houses and Businesses" negatives within the "Buildings and Views" sub-subseries are arranged alphabetically by street name and then numerically by address. Most of these photographs are exterior views, but interior scenes of businesses have been filed here in order to keep exterior and interior views of a particular business together. Photographs of products, equipment, people at work, and special events are filed in the "Businesses" sub-subseries when no building exteriors exist or when the address of the business was unknown. Researchers should look both places for photographs of businesses. Although some "see also" references have been added, they are by no means exhaustive. Researchers may also wish to examine the "Motor Vehicles" sub-subseries, which contains photographs of trucks owned by Ann Arbor businesses.
In the University of Michigan subseries, "Buildings and Views" consists of exterior and interior views of buildings, whereas "Colleges, Schools, and Other Divisions" contains photographs of professors and students in laboratories and classrooms as well as group photographs of staff and students.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Automobiles.; Automobile service stations.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Buildings--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Bridgewater (Mich.); Chelsea (Mich.); Churches.; Dexter (Mich.); Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Farms.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Manchester (Mich.); Milan (Mich.); Pittsfield (Mich.: Township); Salem (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Saline (Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Scio (Mich.: Township); Washtenaw County (Mich.); Whitmore Lake (Mich.); Willow Run (Mich.); Women.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Dwellings.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Portrait photographs.
- Negatives-- 4"x5"
  - Ann Arbor
    - Airports and Airplanes
      - Hammond Aircraft Corporation airplanes June 15, 1933, 4 negatives (Box 1)
        [see also print]
      - Planes April 20, 1934, 3 negatives (Box 1)
      - Men and gliders July 11, 1935, 11 negatives (Box 1)
        [see also prints]
      - CAA men with planes circa 1937, 4 negatives (Box 1)
      - Crowell trainer February 13, 1940, 3 negatives (Box 1)
      - CAA Aeronautics: Ann Arbor airport aerial and ground views; classroom scenes; planes February 16, 1940, 17 negatives (Box 1)
      - Storm-damaged airplane November 1940 (Box 1)
      - Airplane in hangar circa 1949 (Box 1)
      - Bob Crawford -- Ann Arbor Airport October 15, 1953, 4 negatives (Box 1)
      - R.T. Brokaw and planes September 6, 1967, 6 negatives (in 4 envelope) (Box 1)
    - Buildings and Views
      - Cemeteries
        - Arborcrest
          - Veterans' plaque 1952, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            [see also 5"x7" negative]
          - Aerial view with Veterans Administration Hospital 1952, 4 negatives (Box 1)
          - circa 1952, 4 negatives (Box 1)
        - Washtenong Memorial Park -- architectural drawings August 6, 1960, 2 negatives (Box 1)
        - Washtenong Memorial Park
          - circa June 1955, 4 negatives (Box 1)
          - Bronze Bible in Chamber of Commerce window September 1955 (Box 1)
          - August 5, 1958, 5 negatives (Box 1)
      - Churches
        - African Methodist Episcopal
          - Bethel AME -- 632 North 4th Avenue
            - Interior September 4, 1940, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Building, congregation, choirs, parsonage(?) July 25, 1957, 39 negatives (Box 1)
        - Assembly of God
          - Evangel Temple -- 409 South Division June 26, 1956 (Box 1)
        - Baptist
          - First Baptist Church -- 502 East Huron -- Roger Williams Guild; new addition; interior April 1953, 3 negatives (Box 1)
        - Catholic
          - St. Mary's Chapel (E. William and Thompson)
            - Exterior and interior with Father Babcock and congregation October 1941, 5 negatives (Box 1)
            - Mass -- interior and exterior January 10, 1951, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior and interior 1951, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior 1952, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Richard Center under construction 1952, 6 negatives (Box 1)
            - Priest and student 1952 (Box 1)
            - Father Richard Center -- exteriors and interiors May 26, 1953, 6 negatives (Box 1)
            - Father Richard Center -- Father McPhillips with students; youth group; library 1953, 7 negatives (Box 1)
            - Basement March 11, 1954 (Box 1)
            - Father Richard Center -- exterior circa May 1955 (Box 1)
            - Father Richard Center interiors (Father McPhillips with students?) circa August 1955 (Box 1)
              [5 negatives]
          - St. Thomas
            - Bishop Mooney, Father Thomas R. Carey and others March 27, 1938, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Church group and youth group circa 1940, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Boys' choir circa 1943, 4 negatives (Box 1)
            - Boy choristers circa December 1943 (Box 1)
            - Exhibits by women's religious orders 1953, 6 negatives (Box 1)
            - Crowning of Virgin Mary May 5, 1955, 4 negatives (Box 1)
            - Rosary service October 11, 1956 (Box 1)
            - Crowning of Virgin Mary 1956, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Priest and congregation January 29, 1957, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Crowning of Virgin Mary May 2, 1957, 4 negatives (Box 1)
            - Honor banquet June 4, 1957, 6 negatives (Box 1)
            - Procession with children October 3, 1957, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Procession and luncheon November 20, 1957, 7 negatives (Box 1)
            - Priest and congregation (Mass?) circa 1957, 3 negatives (Box 1)
        - Christian
          - Memorial Christian Church -- interior and man April 7, 1958, 3 negatives (Box 1)
        - Congregational
          - Ann Arbor Congregational Church
            - Exterior 1938, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior and interior of 1951 addition 1952, 5 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior April 1953, 2 negatives (Box 1)
        - Episcopal
          - St. Andrew's
            - Bishop Page and Reverend Lewis March 22, 1938, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Architects' drawing of parish hall and chapel addition April 9, 1949 (Box 1)
            - Exterior 1949 (Box 1)
            - Rectory and church 1949, 2 negatives (Box 1)
        - Lutheran
          - Lutheran Student Center -- interior February 21, 1959 (Box 1)
          - Lutheran Student Chapel -- 815 South Forest -- exterior and interior circa 1957, 2 negatives (Box 1)
          - Michigan District Lutheran -- 3773 Geddes, staff? circa 1970, 3 negatives (Box 1)
          - Redeemer Lutheran -- exterior 1960s (Box 1)
          - St. Paul's Lutheran -- exterior, Reverend Carl A. Brauer and groups May 22, 1938, 5 negatives (Box 1)
          - Trinity Evangelical Lutheran -- banquet April 12, 1942 (Box 1)
          - University Lutheran Chapel -- 1511 Washtenaw
            - Exterior April 15, 1956, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior and interior June 28, 1956, 3 negatives (Box 1)
          - Miscellaneous
            - Home interior prepared for church service circa August 10, 1942 (Box 1)
            - Lutheran groups August 1955, 2 negatives (Box 1)
        - Methodist
          - First Methodist Church -- State and Huron
            - Old church -- exterior December 15, 1937 (Box 1)
            - Church steeple being taken down February 24, 1938, 4 negatives (Box 1)
            - New church -- exterior November 3, 1941 (Box 1)
            - New church -- exterior, early 1940s (Box 1)
            - Choir 1946 (Box 1)
            - Exterior and interior 1948, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Interior circa 1953, 2 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior circa 1956, 3 negatives (Box 1)
            - Choirs April 23, 1961, 3 negatives (Box 1)
          - West Side Methodist
            - Interior 1952 (Box 1)
          - Miscellaneous
            - Crusade for Christ -- Reverend Voorhies circa 1950 (Box 1)
            - Reverend Frank L. Fitch, district superintendent, Methodist Church circa 1951 (Box 1)
        - Mormon Chapel -- 2141 Brockman Blvd. circa 1954 (Box 1)
        - Presbyterian
          - First Presbyterian
            - Meetings, meal being served, children playing outside March 5, 1939, 6 negatives (Box 1)
            - Adult and youth groups, small children February 27, 1940, 9 negatives (Box 1)
            - Exterior, choirs, meetings, recreation room March 9, 1940, 13 negatives (Box 1)
            - Mother's Day -- women of church May 12, 1940, 4 negatives (Box 1)
            - Pageant and cookout July 14, 1940, 5 negatives (Box 1)
          - Presbyterian chapel (Verdouin) circa 1941 (Box 1)
          - Presbyterian choir June 1948 (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Our Lady of Fatima statue 1951 (Box 1)
          - Drawing for church by Howard Associates July 2, 1971 (Box 1)
      - Gas Stations
        - Gulf
          - 325 W. Liberty -- exterior and interior with attendants February 20, 1939, 4 negatives (Box 1)
          - 1500 E. Stadium (Packard) -- Schuon's 1951, 2 negatives (Box 1)
          - 1202 South University (at Church Street)
            - Manausa's June 1948 (Box 1)
            - 1948 (Box 1)
          - Unidentified -- display window circa 1940s, 2 negatives (Box 1)
        - Hi-Speed (Abbott Gasoline Company)
          - Broadway and Moore 1949, 4 negatives (Box 1)
          - Unidentified
            - October 13, 1950 (Box 1)
            - 1950 (Box 1)
            - 1952 (Box 1)
        - Michigamme Oil Company -- Division and Huron 1930s
          - 1930s (Box 1)
          - Undated (Box 1)
        - Mobil
          - 1301 South University (at Forest) -- Gainsley's circa 1960 (Box 1)
          - 201 North Main at Ann -- Gee Super Service 1953 (Box 1)
        - Shell -- 1200 Packard -- Frank Agar circa May 1955 (Box 1)
        - Sinclair -- 716 Packard at State -- Paul Reed August 25, 1953 (Box 1)
        - Speedway "79" -- 3160 Washtenaw? circa 1951 (Box 1)
        - Staebler -- 444 S. State Street
          - circa 1933, 2 negatives (Box 1)
          - circa 1934, 1 negatives (Box 1)
        - Standard
          - 601 Packard at Hill -- Golden's July 1953 (Box 1)
          - South University and Forest circa 1960 (Box 1)
        - Sunoco
          - 438 W. Huron at Chapin -- George W. Camp's 1950s (Box 1)
          - 2630 Jackson Avenue -- Chet's circa 1950s (Box 1)